<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shell on Explore my world</title><link>https://surajcm.github.io/blog/tags/shell/</link><description>Recent content in Shell on Explore my world</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://surajcm.github.io/blog/tags/shell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Part 2: Beyond grep: Turbocharging Text Search with Command-Line Wizards</title><link>https://surajcm.github.io/blog/post/enhancing_grep_with_other_tools/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://surajcm.github.io/blog/post/enhancing_grep_with_other_tools/</guid><description>
&lt;h1 id="introduction-to-other-tools">Introduction to Other Tools:&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Let's get familiarized with a few tools that can augment and enhance grep's functionalities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tr-character-transformation">tr: Character Transformation:&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;code>tr&lt;/code> is a command-line utility used for translating or deleting characters in a text stream. It operates on a per-character basis, allowing you to replace or remove specific characters from input text. With its simple syntax and powerful functionality, &lt;code>tr&lt;/code> is commonly used for tasks such as character set conversion, text normalization, and line-ending conversion.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Part 1: Mastering grep: Unleashing the Power of Text Search</title><link>https://surajcm.github.io/blog/post/exploring_grep_and_its_flags/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://surajcm.github.io/blog/post/exploring_grep_and_its_flags/</guid><description>
&lt;h1 id="introduction-to-grep">Introduction to grep:&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>grep&lt;/code> is a handy command-line tool that allows you to search for specific words or patterns within text files. Whether you're looking for a particular phrase in a document, hunting for errors in a log file, or even trying to find a specific line in a long list, grep can quickly pinpoint the information you need. It's like having a powerful search engine for your computer's files, helping you find needles in haystacks with ease.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>